Hi everyone, my name is Jiun.
Welcome to my channel and thank you for watching my video.
Today we are going to talk about Volcano Eruption!
Don't skip this video yet!
You are at the right place,
we are still a YouTube Channel for handmade soap.
But the "volcano eruption" that we will be talking about today
is not this type of volcano eruption
but Soap Volcano.
In my previous video of making household soap,
I promised everyone that I will be making a special episode to talk about
why does handmade soap crack,
especially household soap.
But how do we overcome this problem?
Before we begin, let's take a look at some photos
So that everyone has an idea of
how Soap Volcano looks like
First, we come to Google
type the keywords "Soap Volcano" on the search bar.
You can also search the keywords in Mandarin,
These keywords can also help you to find relevant pictures.
But you can find more relevant pictures using English keywords.
First let us take a look at this photo.
The surface of the soap is totally cracked.
The soap is about to volcano out of the mold.
Now you understand
why this phenomenon is known as Soap Volcano right?
Now look at the second picture.
This is more serious,
the soap is blasting out of the mold like lava.
Next we look at the third picture.
We call this phenomenon as Alien Brain.
Because the wrinkles on the top make the surface looks like alien's brain.
I will explain
the cause of this phenomenon later.
The next picture here is what happened in my last video,
the household soap was cracked on top.
When I took this picture,
the soap was still in saponification.
This is the Gel Phase.
But this picture here
shows how the soap looks like after saponification.
The gel phase disappears,
left with a huge crack at the center.
Later I will tell you some of the steps
I have taken during the 2nd time of making the soap
using the same ingredients and mold
and it did not crack.
An absolute success!
So just now we have seen three different degrees of cracked soap tops.
Although the soap in the third picture did not crack,
but the cause for its wrinkles is the same as cracked soap top,
so I will explain them altogether.
So cracked soap tops and Alien Brain are caused by the same problem
which is
overheating.
If you have experience in making handmade soap,
you might realize that after filling the mold with soap for 30 minutes to 1 hour
the mold container will feels hot.
This is because the soap continues to heat up during saponification.
and if the temperature gets too high,
it will cause Soap Volcano.
The soap is enclosed within the mold
where heat can only escape via the top surface.
So the soap usually cracks
on the top surface.
So what are the other reasons that cause overheating
leading to Soap Volcano?
There are 4 main reasons,
Firstly, the temperature of lye solution and oils was too high during mixing.
Secondly, the mold you are using has very good heat insulating properties.
Thirdly,
you put the soap in places with thermal insulation after it is molded.
For instance, cooler box or oven.
Lastly, you used additives that produce heat naturally.
For example, additives that contain protein,
including cow milk, goat milk, breastmilk and soy milk.
And high natural sugar ingredients,
such as honey.
Additives that contain alcohol
that can be found in the popular beer and wine soaps
and some fragrance oils or essential oils
can also cause the temperature of soap to rise.
Based on my previous experience,
most floral fragrance oils or essential oils  will cause the rise in temperature of soap.
But of course it is not only limited to floral essential oils or fragrance oils,
other essential oils or fragrance oils might also cause the temperature to rise.
But there are countless of essential oils and fragrance oils in the market
and they have complicated ingredients,
so I cannot list them out one-by-one in this video.
Plus I am not a professional perfumer or fragrance expert.
I can only share my knowledge based on my past experience,
so feel free to comment down below if you have anything to add on.
So now let's us talk about
how to prevent cracked soap tops or Soap Volcano.
There are 6 points to share with you:
Number 1: Keep the temperature of the mixture of lye solutions and oils around 30 degree celsius.
Slight difference in temperature should be fine,
but if you are making household soap,
it is best to keep the temperature below 30 degree celsius.
Number 2: choose a less insulating mold.
For instance, silicone molds with thinner walls
or non-wood loaf mold.
Number 3: you can choose not to insulate your newly-molded soap during the summer
and put it at a dry and cool place if needed.
Number 4:
Avoid using naturally heat-producing additives,
the ones we mentioned previously,
those ingredients that contain protein,
sugar,
and alcohol,
as well as some essential oils or fragrance oils.
Number 5: increase the ratio of water
or increase the ratio of soft oils.
When the amount of water increases, the saponification process will get slower
and the heating process will also become slower,
thus reducing the likelihood of cracking.
However, the soap will get overly soft if you add too much water.
Please take this into consideration as well.
But if you increase the ratio of soft oils,
the soap will not be too hardened,
and it will not crack easily.
Number 6:
If you are making handmade soap with high proportion of coconut oil,
for instance, coconut oil household soap.
Then you can consider
cooling the soap using electronic fan.
Or you can put the soap into the fridge to help it cool down.
It's the compartment of the fridge where you put your fruits and vegetables,
please take note!
The example I am giving here is the handmade soap with high proportion of coconut oil
which means not all handmade soaps are suitable to be placed into fridge for cooling.
For instance,
if the proportion of coconut oil is around 80% to 100% in a soap,
then the proportion is considered high.
Among all the handmade soap recipes,
the coconut oil recipe
is most likely to cause cracked tops or Soap Volcano.
Coconut oil is considered a hard oil which induces fast saponification and speeds up the heating process.
If you are making a 100% coconut oil household soap,
the recipe does not contain soft oil at all.
And if you use a mold with good thermal insulating properties...
You might think that it's weird
to put soap into the fridge for cooling,
especially for Asian soapmakers.
But this is actually a very common method in Western countries.
I myself have tried this method
and my household soap was successfully made.
There are indeed some differences in soap making methods
between Western and Eastern countries.
For instance, Western soapmakers usually preheat the oven,
turn off the oven
and then only place the soap into oven to keep it warm.
However, we Asians usually use cooler box to keep the soap warm。
To keep the soap warm,
we put it into the oven.
For cooling purposes,
we put it into the fridge.
There's no problem at all!
You can try it yourself if you are interested,
but remember safety comes first.
Do sufficient research before trying out this method.
Now I will have to further explain
the method that I have mentioned earlier
requires certain flexibility and adaptibility.
Since everyone has different living conditions,
you have to make adjustments
according to your surrounding temperature, climate and the soap making tools you use.
To give you a better idea,
I will provide a few examples.
For instance, imagine it's summer now
and your soap mixture is around 40 degrees celsius,
then your soap is very likely to crack
under such high temperatures.
Now you can choose to use molds with thinner walls
and choose not to insulate the newly-molded soap.
Because according to what I know,
some of the soapmaker
like to make soap under the temperature of around 40 degrees celsius.
By this time,
you don't have to force yourself to change this habit
by reducing the temperature to 30 degrees celsius.
You can choose to make adjustments on
the type of mold, the water portion and the storage place after molding.
But imagine it's winter now,
and the only mold you have is thin-walled mold,
what should you do then?
You can keep the temperature of soap mixture higher in the beginning of soapmaking process
or add some milk to help raise the temperature
and put the mold into cooler box to keep it warm.
However, if you use this type of mold with thicker walls
and with wonden box and lid
then you can choose not to insulate the soap.
I will give one more example of household soap
because household soap really cracks easily
which is especially challenging for newbies.
If the mold you use for making household soap
is a thin-walled mold like this
or a PP5 plastic container like this
they have very good heat dissipating properties,
so the soap will not crack easily under such conditions
and there is no need to put the soap into fridge for cooling.
But if you use mold with good insulating properties like this,
there is a high possibility of soap cracking.
Now you can consider
to cool down the soap
by putting it into the fridge
or placing it in front of a fan.
Of course you have to take your surrounding temperature into account
to see if it's necessary to exercise this step.
The steps for making handmade soap might seem easy,
but there are a lot of details and principles that we need to take into account.
The best way to improve
is to practice regularly
or watch more of my videos.
Do you like videos of me sharing about soapmaking knowledge?
I will share more videos like this if you are interested.
Feel free to drop a comment down below.
If you like this video,
don't forget to hit the like button below,
subscribe my channel and turn on the notification.
Thank you for watching! See you in my next video!